How good are you at maths?
你数学学的怎么样？
Some people love the challenge of algebra or enjoy working out number puzzles such as Sudoko.
有些人喜欢代数带来的挑战，或是热衷于钻研数独这类数字谜题。
Maths is all around us, from working out how to split the bill after a meal, to calculating your household bills.
数学其实无处不在，从饭后算清楚如何分摊账单，到核算家庭开支，都离不开它。
But many dread the moment when they have to deal with numbers and figures and feel a real sense of worry and confusion.
但也有很多人一碰到数字和数据就犯怵，内心满是焦虑与困惑。
It can seem daunting, but this ‘maths anxiety’ is perfectly normal, and you’re definitely not alone.
这件事看似让人却步，但这种“数学焦虑”其实非常正常，你绝对不是一个人在面对。
And anyway, our worries and fears don’t necessarily reflect our ability.
而且，我们的担忧与恐惧，并不一定能反映出真实的能力水平。
The problem really starts in childhood, at school.
这个问题其实从童年时期的校园生活就开始了。
Research has found that maths teachers who are nervous about teaching the subject can pass on their anxiety to the pupils, and girls may be more likely to be affected.
研究发现，那些在教授数学时感到紧张的老师，会把自己的焦虑情绪传递给学生，而且女生受到的影响可能会更大。
The Programme for International Student Assessment found around 31% of 15 and 16-year-olds across 34 countries said they got very nervous doing maths problems, 33% said they got tense doing maths homework, and nearly 60% said they worried maths classes would be difficult.
国际学生评估项目的调查显示，在34个国家的15至16岁青少年中，约31%的人表示做数学题时会极度紧张，33%的人称做数学作业时会感到焦虑，近60%的人则担心数学课会很难。
Shulamit Kahn, from Boston University’s Questrom School of Business, told the BBC she believes giving students, particularly girls, good role models “is critical, especially at a young age”.
波士顿大学奎斯特罗姆商学院的舒拉米特·卡恩在接受BBC采访时表示，她认为给学生们——尤其是女生——树立好的榜样“至关重要，尤其是在年纪还小的时候”。
She thinks the key is to get people, especially women, who love teaching maths to younger children.
她认为，关键是要让那些喜欢教数学的人，尤其是女性，来给低龄儿童上课。
Writing for BBC Future, David Robson says “It’s not clear why maths arouses so much fear compared to geography.
大卫·罗布森在为BBC未来频道撰稿时提到：“目前还不清楚为什么数学会比地理更容易引发恐惧。
But the fact that there’s a right or wrong answer – there’s no room for bluffing – might make you more worried about underperforming.”
但数学题非对即错——没有蒙混过关的余地——这一点可能会让人们更加担心自己表现不佳。”
And once we assume we’re not a ‘maths person’, we avoid solving things that we probably could do.
而且一旦我们认定自己不是“学数学的料”，就会刻意回避那些其实自己完全有能力解决的数学问题。
Psychologists have been trying to work out why mental arithmetic can bring us out in a sweat.
心理学家们一直在试图弄明白，为什么心算会让人紧张得冒汗。
That seed of fear may come from many sources, but some suggest that articulating your fears can loosen their hold on you, and encourage children to see a maths test as a challenge, not a threat.
这种恐惧的种子可能来自很多方面，但一些专家指出，把自己的恐惧说出来，就能减轻它的影响；同时，要鼓励孩子们把数学考试看作一种挑战，而非威胁。
Ideally, we need to think positively about maths and give it a second chance.
理想情况下，我们需要以积极的心态看待数学，再给它一次机会。